So, I'm afraid.
حسنًا، أنا خائف.
Right now,
في هذه اللحظة،
on this stage,
على المنصة،
I feel fear.
أِشعر بالخوف.
In my life, I ain't met many people
لم أقابل في حياتي الكثير من الناس
that will readily admit when they are afraid.
على استعداد أن يقرّوا بالخوف حال شعورهم به.
And I think that's because deep down,
وأعتقد أن السبب أنهم في قرارة أنفسهم،
they know how easy it spreads.
يعلمون سهولة انتشاره.
See, fear is like a disease.
كما ترون، الخوف مثل المرض.
When it moves, it moves like wildfire.
عندما ينتشر، فهو ينتشر كما النيران في الغابات.
But what happens when,
ولكن ما يحدث حينها،
even in the face of that fear,
حتى عند مواجهة ذلك الخوف،
you do what you've got to do?
تفعل ما يجب عليك فعله
That's called courage.
تلك هي الشجاعة.
And just like fear,
ومثل الخوف تمامًا،
courage is contagious.
فإن الشجاعة معدية.
See, I'm from East St. Louis, Illinois.
كما ترون، أنا من شرق سانت لويس، إلينوي.
That's a small city
مدينة صغيرة
across the Mississippi River from St. Louis, Missouri.
عبر نهر المسيسيبي من سانت لويس، ميسوري.
I have lived in and around St. Louis my entire life.
عشت كل حياتي في سانت لويس وحولها.
When Michael Brown, Jr.,
عندما أطلقت الشرطة النيران
an ordinary teenager,
على المراهق مايكل براون،
was gunned down by police in 2014 in Ferguson, Missouri --
في العام 2014 في فيجيسون بولاية ميسوري --
another suburb, but north of St. Louis --
وهي ضاحية أخرى في شمالي سانت لويس --
I remember thinking,
كنت أفكر حينها،
he ain't the first,
أنه لم يكن الأول،
and he won't be the last young kid to lose his life to law enforcement.
كما أنه لن يكون آخر فتى يفقد حياته بسبب فرض القانون.
But see, his death was different.
لكن كما ترون، كانت وفاته مختلفة.
When Mike was killed,
عندما قتل مايك،
I remember the powers that be trying to use fear as a weapon.
أتذكر السلطات التي كانت تحاول استخدام الخوف كسلاح.
The police response to a community in mourning was to use force
استخدمت قوات الشرطة التي واجهت الجموع في الصباح القوة
to impose fear:
لفرض الخوف:
fear of militarized police,
الخوف من الشرطة المسلحة،
imprisonment,
الحبس،
fines.
الغرامات.
The media even tried to make us afraid of each other
حتى أن الإعلام حاول أن يزرع الخوف بيننا
by the way they spun the story.
عن طريق تحويرهم للقصة.
And all of these things have worked in the past.
كل هذه الأشياء نجحت في الماضي.
But like I said, this time it was different.
لكن كما قلت، هذه المرة الوضع مختلف.
Michael Brown's death and the subsequent treatment of the community
وفاة مايكل براون والمعاملة اللاحقة التي واجهها المجتمع
led to a string of protests in and around Ferguson and St. Louis.
قادت كلها إلى سلسلة من الاحتجاجات في كل من فيرجسون وسانت لويس وما جاورهما.
When I got out to those protests about the fourth or fifth day,
عندما شاركت في هذه الاحتجاجات في اليوم الرابع أو الخامس،
it was not out of courage;
لم يكن ذلك بدافع الشجاعة؛
it was out of guilt.
بل بدافع الذنب.
See, I'm black.
كما ترون، فأنا أسود.
I don't know if y'all noticed that.
لا أعرف إن لاحظتم ذلك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But I couldn't sit in St. Louis, minutes away from Ferguson,
لكني لا أستطيع أن أجلس في سانت لويس على بعد دقائق من فيرجسون،
and not go see.
من دون أن أذهب لإلقاء نظرة.
So I got off my ass to go check it out.
لذا، تحركت لأرى ما يحدث.
When I got out there,
عندما وصلت إلى هناك،
I found something surprising.
وجدت شيئًا مفاجئًا.
I found anger; there was a lot of that.
شهدت الغضب؛ كان هناك الكثير من الغضب.
But what I found more of was love.
ولكن كان الحب هو سيد الموقف.
People with love for themselves.
حب الناس لأنفسهم.
Love for their community.
حبهم لمجتمعهم.
And it was beautiful --
ولقد كان الأمر رائعًا --
until the police showed up.
إلى أن أتت الشرطة.
Then a new emotion was interjected into the conversation:
فاقتحمت عاطفة جديدة شكل الحوار:
fear.
الخوف.
Now, I'm not going to lie;
لن أكذب الآن؛
when I saw those armored vehicles,
عندما رأيت تلك العربات المسلحة،
and all that gear
وكل تلك المعدات
and all those guns
وكل تلك الأسلحة
and all those police
وكل رجل الشرطة أولئك
I was terrified --
شعرت بالذعر --
personally.
على المستوى الشخصي.
And when I looked around that crowd,
وعندما نظرت ناحية ذلك الحشد،
I saw a lot of people that had the same thing going on.
رأيت العديد من الناس يعتريهم نفس الخوف.
But I also saw people with something else inside of them.
ولكني رأيت أناسًا آخرين يعتريهم شيء آخر.
That was courage.
كانت تلك هي الشجاعة.
See, those people yelled,
ترونهم يهتفون،
and they screamed,
ويصرخون،
and they were not about to back down from the police.
ولم يبدوا عليهم التراجع أبدًا أمام الشرطة.
They were past that point.
كانوا متقدمين.
And then I could feel something in me changing,
حينها شعرت بشيء في داخلي يتغير،
so I yelled and I screamed,
فبدأت أهتف وأصرخ،
and I noticed that everybody around me was doing the same thing.
ولاحظت أن الجميع حولي كانوا يفعلون المثل.
And there was nothing like that feeling.
وما من شيء كان يضاهي ذلك الشعور.
So I decided I wanted to do something more.
لذا، قررت حينها أنني أود فعل شيء آخر.
I went home, I thought: I'm an artist. I make shit.
عدت أدراجي، فكرت: أنا فنان، أنتج فنًا.
So I started making things specific to the protest,
بدأت حينها أصنع أشياء خصيصًا للاحتجاجات،
things that would be weapons in a spiritual war,
أشياء ترقى لكونها أسلحة في حربٍ روحية،
things that would give people voice
أشياء ستعطي الناس صوتًا
and things that would fortify them for the road ahead.
ومن شأنها أن تحصّنهم في الخطوات القادمة.
I did a project where I took pictures of the hands of protesters
بدأت مشروعًا حيث التقطت صورًا لأيدي المحتجّين
and put them up and down the boarded-up buildings
وألصقتها على طول المباني
and community shops.
والمحلات التجارية.
My goal was to raise awareness and to raise the morale.
كانت هدفي هو نشر الوعي ورفع القيم.
And I think, for a minute at least,
وأعتقد أنه لدقيقة على الأقل،
it did just that.
نجح ذلك الأمر.
Then I thought, I want to uplift the stories of these people
فكّرت بعدها، أنّي أريد أن أنهض بقصص أولئك الناس
I was watching being courageous in the moment.
الذين شاهدتهم يظهرون الشجاعة في تلك اللحظة.
And myself and my friend,
وثّقت أنا وصديقي،
and filmmaker and partner Sabaah Folayan
صانع الأفلام والشريك ساباح فولايان،
did just that with our documentary,
وثّقنا لذلك في فلمنا الوثائقي،
"Whose Streets?"
"لمن الشوارع؟"
I kind of became a conduit
أصبحت كقناةٍ نوعًا ما
for all of this courage that was given to me.
لكل تلك الشجاعة التي اكتسبتها.
And I think that's part of our job as artists.
وأعتقد أن ذلك جزء من عملنا كفنانين.
I think we should be conveyors of courage in the work that we do.
أعتقد أننا لا بد أن نصبح ناقلين للشجاعة في العمل الذي نقوم به.
And I think that we are the wall between the normal folks
كما أعتقد أننا الجدار الفاصل بين الناس العاديين
and the people that use their power to spread fear and hate,
وأولئك الذين يستخدمون سلطتهم لنشر الخوف والكراهية،
especially in times like these.
بالذات في أوقات كهذه.
So I'm going to ask you.
لذا سألقي عليكم سؤالًا.
Y'all the movers and the shakers,
أنتم صانعو الأحداث،
you know, the thought leaders:
تعرفون، قادة الفكر:
What are you gonna do
ماذا ستفعلون
with the gifts that you've been given
بالملكات التي أعطيتموها
to break us from the fear the binds us every day?
لتحريرنا من الخوف الذي يحيط بنا كل يوم؟
Because, see, I'm afraid every day.
بسبب، كما ترون، أشعر بالخوف كل يوم.
I can't remember a time when I wasn't.
لا أتذكر آخر مرة لم أكن خائفًا فيها.
But once I figured out that fear was not put in me to cripple me,
لكن حينما عرفت أن الخوف لم يكن هناك ليقيدني،
it was there to protect me,
بل ليحميني،
and once I figured out how to use that fear,
وعندما عرفت كيف أستخدم الخوف،
I found my power.
وجدت قوتي.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)